A Guide to the Joseph Sawin Ewing Papers, 1794-1965
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Joseph Sawin Ewing Papers, 1794-1965
Library of Virginia
31871
4.05 cubic feet; 9 boxes; box numbers 1-9
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of John MacDonald Ewing, 1208 Morningside Lane, Alexandria, Virginia, 28 July 1983.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Reverend Joseph Sawin Ewing (1899-1965) was born in Illinois and spent a great part of his life in the midwest and west, serving churches in Oregon, South Dakota, and Oklahoma. A 1922 graduate of the Virginia Theological Seminary, he returned to Virginia in 1950 as rector of South Farnham Parish, Essex County, Virginia. Residing in Tappahannock, he was active in local historical societies and served as president of the Essex County Historical Society in the early 1960s. He became interested in the history of local Indian tribes and early colonial churches, doing research and field work in both areas, locating early sites through records, maps, and local people. He published articles in Northern Neck of Virginia Historical Magazine (1963) and Virginia Magazine of History and Biography (1965).
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1794-1965 (bulk 1950-1965), of Joseph Sawin Ewing, consisting of research notes, correspondence, printed items, and published articles documenting Ewing's interests in genealogy and local history of the Old Rappahannock County (Va.) area. The county existed from 1656 to 1692 and covered present day Essex and Richmond counties and parts of other adjoining counties. There are transcripts of court records, correspondence, information on old homes, towns, families, and villages of Old Rappahannock County, extracts from published sources, and other historical information. Ewing also included King and Queen, King George, Lancaster, Middlesex, New Kent, and Westmoreland counties in his researches. The papers are divided into eight series including, Colonial Church, Correspondence, Indians, Notes, Pioneer Settlements, Research notes for published articles, Rosegill, and Subject files. Ewing's original folder titles have been maintained, along with the original series division. Ewing's method of titling folders appears to have been one of casual notations of content, rather than precise information on materials within the folders. Therefore crosschecking of folders and series is necessary to yield all pertinent information.
Organization
Organized into the following eight series: I. Colonial Church. II. Correspondence. III. Indians. IV. Notes. V. Pioneer settlements. VI. Research notes for published articles. VII. Rosegill. VIII. Subject files.
Contents List
- Colonial Church:
  This series includes notes, maps, outlines, plats, and published materials used in Ewing's 1961 lecture series on the colonial church in Virginia.Ewing lectured at the Grace Episcopal Church (Alexandria, Va.) and the Abingdon Men's Club (Abingdon, Va.), among other places. Included are notes on Lancaster Parish (Middlesex County, Virginia), South Farnham Parish (Essex County, Virginia), and Upper Piscataway Parish (Old Rappahannock County, Virginia).
  - Church road and Church road swamp (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Church sites (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Glebes and poor house tracts (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lancaster Parish (Middlesex County, Va.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Leedstown Church and Occupatia Church (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lecture #1, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lecture #2, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lecture #3, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Lecture #4, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Lecture #5, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Lecture #6, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letter, Andrew Syme to William Latane, 1794 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Reading notes (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - South Farnham Parish (Essex County, Va.) (Box 1, Folder 15-19)
  - Talks on colonial church (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Upper Piscataway church sites (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Correspondence:
  This series includes correspondence from genealogists researching families in Essex, King and Queen, King George, Lancaster, Middlesex, New Kent, Richmond, and Westmoreland counties, Virginia.Correspondents include Stephen F. Bayne Jr., Laurance S. Brigham, Lawrence L. Brown, George MacLaren Brydon, George H.S. King, Howard McCord, George Carrington Mason, and Peter Quennel.
  - Bayne, Stephen, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Essex County families, 1955-1964 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Essex County families, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Mason, George, 1952-1962 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Matthews family, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Rosier family, 1961-1965 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Smith family, 1957-1963 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Indians:
  This series includes correspondence, clippings, maps, notes, and publications Ewing gathered on the Rappahannock Indians.Includes copy of the publication "Indian Sites below the falls of the Rappahannock, Virginia," by David Bushnell, correspondence, newsletters, and quarterly bulletins from the Archeological Society of Virginia, and a paper written by Joseph Ewing, Margaret Ewing, and Helen Rountree entitled, "Indian towns in Virginia's Rappahannock River Valley, 1608-1800." Also includes information on the Mattaponi Indians.
  - Archaeological Society of Virginia, 1950-1964 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - David Bushnell's book (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1953-1964 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Indian towns in the Virginia Rappahannock River Valley, 1608-1800" (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Mattoponi Indian town (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Movement of Indians (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Piscataway (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Rappahannock River tribes and towns (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Notes:
  This series contains miscellaneous notes regarding Essex and Richmond counties, Virginia. The folders are labeled according to the source of the information.Folder titles include Essex County land tax lists and order books, Mutual Assurance Society of Virginia records, chancery cases, Colonial Records Project, and the Webb family papers.
  - Acts establishing towns and ports (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Chancery boxes (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Colonial period (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Colonial parish and county records (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Colonial Records project (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Essex County land tax list (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Essex County order books (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Essex County order books (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Essex County processioners book (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Fleet, Beverly (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Harrison, Fairfax (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Hening, William (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Land records, miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Mutual Assurance Society of Virginia (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Richmond County, Virginia (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - School, George (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Sweeney's wills (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Webb family papers (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Wright's notes (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 3, Folder 8-10)
  - Needs investigation (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - To be checked (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Pioneer Settlements:
  This series includes notes on the neighborhoods resulting from the Lancaster County court order of 6 August 1653, which created Rappahannock County and appointed ten commissioners to oversee the local muster. The order described the muster limits, which included the home plantation of each commissioner. These neighborhoods are numbered by Ewing and listed geographically from the lower end of the north side of the Rappahannock River to the upper section, and from the lower end of the south side of the river to the upper section.Ewing's folder titles have been maintained as well as the original arrangement of the folders after determining the subject's location on the north or south side of the Rappahannock River. Materials within these folders contain general information on land transfers and ownership of a particular piece of land.
  - General
    - Source material (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - I. North Side, Corotoman River mouth to mouth of Rappahannock River/Christ Church area (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - II. North Side, Upper side Corotoman River to Thomas Brice's (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - III. North Side, Thomas Brice's north to county line (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - IV. North Side, County line/Farnham Creek to upper side Totusky Creek (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - V. North Side, Catgut to Pepetick Creek, Leedstown to Bray's Church (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - VI. North Side, Leedstown to head of river (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - I. South Side, Christ Church/Saluda to mouth/Old Piankatank Point (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - II. South Side, South of LaGrange creek to Saluda and Christ Church (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - III. South Side, North side of LaGrange creek to county line (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - IV. South Side, North from county line including Puscoticion creek (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - IVa. South Side, Purcatacon/Piscataway (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - V. South Side, North side of Piscataway (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Va. South Side, Pioneers on Hoskins (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - VI. South Side, Occupason creek to head of river (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - North Side
    - Downman, Deschamps, Sydnor, Grittith, Davis, Woolard, Stonum (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Woolard, Smith (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Peacock's, Mar's Hill, Fauntleroy, Northern, B. McCarty, Swan (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Belle Mount, Belfields, Mitchell's (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Peachy (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Baileys, Downman family (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - John Davis, upper part of Luke Milner's, Mark Milner to Thomas Hammond, Le Roy Dobyns, George Davis (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Hodgkin, Hayden, Travers (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Fauntleroy, Farnham Creek patents, Farnham plantation (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Farnham, maps and plats (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Downman (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Downman Hall (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Farnham River front (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Windsor, Farnham Glebe, North Farnham Church (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Durrettsville, Miskill, Calvary M.E. Church (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Cedar Grove, Nicholas Flood (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Farnham Creek notes (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Jones, Edward (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Edgehill and Bowerhill (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Farnham's Hall, George Payne, Chelsea (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Farnham house tract (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Woodford (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Cabinete Hall, Hornsby Manor (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Peacock's quarter (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Appleby's (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Robert Hopkins and Henry Fleets patents, north side of Rappahannock, Fleet's, Catpoint's creek (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Fauntleroy and William Lloyd, Stonehouse, Mangorite, Naylors, Rappahannock creek (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - William Underwood, James Williamson, Robert Tomlin, Meader's, John Sherlock (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - John Hull, forks of the Tutsky, Richmond Hill, Garland's mill pond, Indian field, Rich Neck, Charles B. Carter's estate (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - South Side
    - Smith, Nicholas (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Webb family (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Tappahannock Masonic Lodge (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Hobb's Hole (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Essex County history talk (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Peachy, William (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Back of Miles End, from river, below Piscataway (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Corbin Hill (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Catch Penny (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Payne and Tony Smith's land (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - South Hill (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Waterview and Belleview, Young, Gatewood, Tuscararora, Waring (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - John Robinson family (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Toby Smith, Ashland, Paradise, Hill Park, Peachy's, Oake, Joshua Fry, Browne's (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Baughan, James (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Essex County, Virginia (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Paul's Cross roads, north side of Old Mill Road, Woods, Banks, Conners (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Paul's Cross Roads, Gordons, south side of Old Mill Road (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Mussel creek, up and including New Glasgow, Rich Neck, Deep Landing, Sandy Landing (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Wood, Thomas (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Western branch, later deeds, Piscataway, south side (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Dunns Mill, Matthews bridge (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Middle branch of Piscataway (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Covington, Jones, Claiborne, Minor (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Jones Point, Rice Jones estate, Montagues, Mount Prospect, Rose Hill, Mount Comfort, Layton's, below glebe (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - People, plantations, and land, Essex and King and Queen, Miller's Tavern, to St. Paul's, to Haile's bridge (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Goodrich, Mt. Maple, Fleet, Crow, etc. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Clark family (George Rogers) (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Location of pioneers on Piscataway, north side (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Bowler's family, Mt. Verde, Corbin Hill, Adcock, Latane's, Slaughter, Peachy, Janey (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Piscataway Old Mill Road, on both sides, north side of Piscataway Creek, Halsey, Bray's (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Road to Piscataway Ferry, on both sides of road, north side Piscataway Creek, William Johnson, south half of Young's, south end of Church Road (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Bray family (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Clements, Mt. Clements, Dr. John Pittman, Poplar Spring, Henry Mace, George H. Dobyns (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Daingerfield, Reeves, Gillette, Button (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Edmondson family (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - South side church road, swamp, small tracts, Beazley plat 1856, road to Church Hill, Burke plat 1810, Kemps plat purchased by Moses Crow, Burnetts (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Bridge branch of Piscataway, The Meadow, Allen's, Roane's, Mt. Maple, Edwin Upshaw's holding, Bohannans and Mill (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Meador, Thomas (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Gregory, John (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Meadoe's bridge, Paynefield, Prospect Hill, Gregory's, Daingerfield Mill (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - James Taylor, Gregory, Pendleton and Taylor (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Henry Aubrey's land, James Taylor's land (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Henry Reeves land (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Edwin Thacker's patent (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Gatewood's (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Elizabeth Reeves Allen's land (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Mahockney, etc. (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Timberlake papers, Judge Lomax, William Daingerfield, Belvedere (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Blake family (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Brockenbrough family (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Archibald Ritchies manor house and lots in Tappahannock (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Henley house (Tappahannock) (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Coleman's land (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Goodrich, Griffings, Ritchies, Scandrett, Jones, Pitts, McCall's, Henley, Micou (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - North side of Hoskins (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Upper Piscataway, north of Hoskins creek (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Roane family (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Rappahannock river (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Lewis family (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Gregories, Prospect Hill, Mt. Landing (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Brooke family (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Waring notes (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Beverly family (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Families in St. Anne's Parish (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Gouldman family (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Skinkers Neck and Moores Mount, Moss Neck and Corbins, Taliaferro's Mount, Charles Grymes and Richard White (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Research notes for published articles:
  This series includes drafts and notes from articles written by Ewing, including "The First Justices in the Rappahannock River and the Formation of Rappahannock County," published in 1963 in the Northern Neck of Virginia Historical Magazine (Vol. 13, December 1963, pp. 1182-1194) and "The Correspondence of Archibald McCall and George McCall," published in 1965 in Virginia Magazine of History and Biography (Vol. 73, July and October 1965, pp. 312-353, 425-454). Included are notes, footnotes, drafts, and final drafts.
  - "The First Justices in the Rappahannock River and the Formation of Rappahannock County."
    - Draft (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Draft and notes (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - First draft (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Final corrected draft (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Final draft (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - List of colonial justices (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Notes (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Notes, Bertrand and first lower court house (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Notes, Gentleman justices, clerks, etc. (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Notes, Justices of Old Rappahannock and Essex Counties (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Notes, Old Rappahannock county justices and court orders (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Speech (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - "The Correspondence of Archibald McCall and George McCall."
    - Abstracts (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Footnotes (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Footnotes and introduction (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Footnotes, 2nd writing (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Footnotes for the letters and introduction (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Letter transcripts (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Letter transcripts (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Manuscript, Footnotes for introduction (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Manuscript, Footnotes (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Manuscript, Introduction (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Manuscript, Letters I-X (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Manuscript, Letters XI-XXIII (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Notes (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Other notes, deeds, orders, family notes, etc. (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Rosegill:
  This series includes notes, clippings, published materials, maps, and an outline for a paper about the Wormley family plantation of Rosegill in Middlesex County, Virginia.
  - Draft and clippings (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Draft (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Notes (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Subject files:
  This series contains clippings, notes, maps, and correspondence on a variety of subjects including Bacon's Rebellion, biographies on Henry Fleet and George Washington, highway markers in Essex County, mills, naval officers and collectors of revenue in the rivers, roads and ferries, swamps and creeks, and tobacco.
  - Bacon's Rebellion (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Biography (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 6-8)
    - Fleet, Henry (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Biography- Washington, George (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Court houses (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Doctors (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Highway markers in Essex County (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Leedstown Resolution (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Maps (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Merchants and shipping (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Mills (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Naval officers and collectors of revenue in the rivers (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Plats (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Roads and ferries (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Schools, colonial (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Swamps and creeks (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Tobacco (Box 9, Folder 21)